When I started looking
into Effect, I started seeing,
Well, this has a lot of promise and
potential if you use
it in the right way.
What I mean by that is you don't have to
necessarily go from 0%
to 100% overnight.
You don't have to completely
redesign the entire application
to take advantage of some of the benefits
that Effect has to offer.
That's how I started, was incrementally
adopting Effect in
parts of the code base.
And this was really
what enabled it to work.
Welcome to Cause & Effect,
a podcast about the TypeScript library
and ecosystem called Effect,
helping engineers to build
production-ready software.
I'm your host, Johannes Schickling, and
I've been building with
Effect for over four years.
With this podcast, I want to help others
understand the powers and
benefits of using Effect.
In this episode, I'm talking to David
Golightly, who's a Staff
Engineer at MasterClass.
In this conversation, we explore how
David has built Cortex,
MasterClass's AI voice chat system,
leveraging Effect streams heavily
to build a cutting-edge AI
experience. Let's get into it.
Hey David, so great to have you on the
podcast. How are you doing?
Doing great. Thanks for having me.
I'm really excited. The two of us had the
pleasure to now meet in person twice in
the course of the last half a year.
The first time we've met in person was at
the Effect TypeScript
Meetup in San Francisco.
And then a couple of weeks ago, we had
the pleasure to meet again in beautiful
Italy in Livorno, where you've also given
a talk about Cortex and what you're
building at MasterClass.
And it was such a pleasure to spend a
bunch of time together and talk about all
things TypeScript related beyond.
You also have some beautiful music gear
in the background. But today we're going
to talk about how you're
using Effect at MasterClass.
So would you mind introducing yourself
and sharing your background?
Yeah, sure. My name is David Golightly. I
am a Staff Engineer at MasterClass.
And I've been in the industry building
mostly web applications for
about almost 18 years now.
I've also dabbled in some mobile
applications, some back end, some other
embedded applications over the years.
But my main focus has been first
in the JavaScript world and then more
recently in the TypeScript
world for the last several years.
My actual background, though, I don't
have a Computer Science degree. My
education is in music.
And I grew up
surrounded by pianos.
My father is a piano technician and also
a piano professor who plays
classical, you know, everything you could
think of classical music.
He has played it. You know, he's played
with orchestras and he's, you know,
played solo concerts and chamber music.
And so forth. So just steeped in
classical music growing up in pianos and
also in repairing pianos, which I found
somehow translated
into programming sort of.
You're doing a lot of really repetitive
tasks. You have 88 keys. You have 230
some strings on a regular piano.
So there's a lot of repetitive tasks and
you quickly figure out ways to work more
efficiently when
you're doing piano repair.
So later on, after I got my degree in
music, I found that it wasn't well, well,
music is a passion of mine and it's
something that I still do.
It's not something I want to try to make
a career in. And so I quickly discovered
that, well,
programming is just right there.
And I actually enjoy doing it somewhat.
And so I devoted some energy into
learning how to do that professionally.
And, you know, all these
years later, here I am.
That is awesome. And such a funny
parallel since we never talked about
this, but my mother also
happens to be a professor in piano.
And so I likewise also grew up surrounded
by pianos and played the piano for quite
a while, but then also found myself more
attractive to technology.
But I think this is a fairly common
overlap of people who had their start in
music or a different kind of art and then
gravitated also towards programming.
And I think it's just a certain way of
like how someone's brain works that
really like there's a couple of people
come to mind to have professional music
background who are just like absolutely
brilliant in the engineering field.
So that's a very funny parallel. But
keeping it a bit more focused on like
Effect, what has brought you to Effect?
How did you first learn about it? And
what did you think about it when you
saw it the first time?
Yeah, so I was not necessarily going to
adopt Effect for the work I was doing,
say, maybe over a year ago,
which was more React focused.
It wasn't something that I was
necessarily considering.
You know, I think React is a
great framework and it totally
transformed how we do
front end development.
But it's not without its problems in
terms of state management and so forth.
But I was mostly happy with it for the
front end and we try to
keep things lightweight there.
But then I got asked to work on this new
project Cortex, which I'll
talk about a little bit more.
And that was going to be a server side
application that was also not a
conventional API server.
Instead, it was managing a lot of async
events, a lot of open WebSockets, more
than one of like several open WebSocket
WebSocket connections that
it needed to then coordinate.
So I was looking at a proof of
concept that somebody else at our company
had built that was really, you
know, what we call async hell.
That is just lots of callbacks, lots of
event listeners passing
around references to random things.
And we're starting to try to build into
it observability and error handling and,
you know, more advanced interruption type
features that involve coordinating the
state of multiple WebSockets.
And it just wasn't going to work.
It was not going to scale.
The implementation was just going to get
increasingly tangled.
And so that's when I started looking
around for, well, what is
the state of the art here?
I had used RxJS in the past.
And I think that, you know, for people
who've used RxJS, when they see Effect,
that's what their first thought is.
Oh, this is RxJS.
I've seen this before.
You know, this is this is familiar to me.
It's just another RxJS kind of knockoff.
I didn't really find it to be the case,
though, for several reasons.
But I think that what really caught my
eye with Effect was the
really active community.
Because when I'm looking to adopt a new
framework that is going to form the
backbone of how we build an application,
I don't want to have to
be inventing stuff out of whole cloth
resurrect things from a couple of
examples that don't
really apply to my application.
I don't want to be in
the dark and be on my own.
And I especially don't want to ask my
teammates to accept a framework where
they don't have the proper
documentation or the guidance.
They don't know where to find help.
And so really, I found that the community
seems to be Effect's biggest asset.
And just how helpful everybody is and how
enthusiastic everybody is
really ease the adoption process.
That is awesome to hear.
And that definitely also reflects my own
perspective and my own reality.
This is what drew me
to Effect very early on.
The community was much smaller at this
point and I tried to play a positive role
in like growing and
forming that community.
But it's also something I'm like super
excited about and super
proud of that we like together.
Yeah, broad Effect to
the point where it is today.
And it attracts more
like brilliant minds.
And it's also interesting that Effect
attracts a lot of experience engineers
like yourself, but also new engineers
that are drawn to
building something great.
And that community is such a compelling
aspect of that as well.
So maybe to linger on the RxJS part for a
little bit since yes, quite a few people
are kind of comparing Effect with RxJS.
For folks who are familiar with RxJS but
not yet with Effect, where would you say
there are parallels and the commonalities
and where would you say
things are much more different?
Well, in RxJS, the idea is
it's very stream oriented.
So you essentially are creating
everything is an observable.
It can emit events.
And this is really useful actually.
I think a lot of programming situations
can be modeled in this way.
You have especially the asynchronous
stuff like really anything side-effectey
is happening asynchronously.
You can't necessarily expect it or
predict it, but then you have to react to
it and do something in response to it.
You have user input,
user loads the web page.
You didn't know when or why
they were going to do that.
They click on a link or they decide to
watch a video or fill out
a form or what have you.
This is ultimately the timing and
coordination of these things
and these inputs are driven by humans.
And likewise, when you have systems where
you have connections coming from third
party services or you have other kinds of
asynchronous behaviors where you have to
connect users to each other.
A lot of the hardest parts of programming
happen when we have asynchronous behavior
that we have to model.
And this is why I think you look at
paradigms like HTTP or more specifically
like a model view controller that you see
in Rails that is still so successful.
And one of the things that that has
largely done is allow us to architect
applications around kind of one shot
actions where you get essentially a
function call via an HTTP request.
And your application now has to implement
the function call and respond with it.
But it's everything that happens between
the request and the response is largely
typically serialized.
It's sequential. It's
not in parallel, right?
Which is great. It makes things a lot
more easy to reason about.
You know, things happen in a sequence A,
B, C, D, E and then you're done.
But most of what we have to deal with,
especially in building web interfaces or
building applications like
Cortex, is not like that.
Because you have a lot of things that can
happen and you might be in the middle of
one thing and then something else happens
that you didn't expect.
And now you have to deal with that. And a
lot of this also involves kind of keeping
state updates going.
This is why honestly, this is why React
superseded jQuery is because they're
really good at this.
But getting back to your question about
RxJS, RxJS is kind of an even more next
level approach at this where you can
model everything as an observable.
You don't know when it's going to happen,
but you know that you might receive one
or more different kind of events.
And then how do you combine events from
one observable with events from another
observable when they need to interact to
produce some sort of output.
And RxJS is really built
around this sort of model.
The thing is though, RxJS is also trying
to be not just RxJS, but it's a reactive
framework that is cross-platform.
So you have the same APIs more or less
that are designed for JavaScript or
TypeScript that are then also ported over
to Java or ported over to Swift or ported
over to Kotlin or ported over to
whatever other language or framework.
And so I think there was an intentional
desire on the part of the designers there
to keep things language agnostic in their
designs, which in my opinion is kind of a
flaw because it means that it's
yes, you can transfer that knowledge
from one language to
another pretty easily.
If you know reactive programming, you can
do it in any language.
But it means that you're passing on a lot
of the strengths of each language that
you're in in order to make things as same
as possible between every
language that you're working in.
Effect in my mind is taking kind of a
very different approach, even though it's
based on the ZIO, which
is the Scala equivalent.
It was the inspiration for Effect.
My understanding is that now, Effect's
design is pretty detached from needing to
keep parity with ZIO.
Effect is basically about TypeScript and
getting really good at TypeScript, making
TypeScript the best it can be.
And there is no, as far as I know, I
can't speak for the core team, but as far
as I know, there's no attempt at saying,
"Well, what if we make Effect
for Java or Swift or Kotlin?"
It's not about that. It's just about what
is TypeScript good at and how can we be
really good at that.
So that's a really big point, I think,
because with RxJS in TypeScript, it never
felt like they really got how to make a
TypeSafe reactive stream
application really work.
the types
kind of sort of worked.
As far as I recall, there wasn't really a
great story around requirements
management or even really error handling
the way there is with Effect.
And so it lacked a lot of the
potential, it failed to take advantage
of a lot of the potential that TypeScript
has to offer in the way that Effect does.
Does that answer your question?
No, it does. And it
reflects also my perspective.
In fact, I've been using ReactiveCocoa
back in the days, and I believe that was
early on in Swift, and it was quite
pleasant to use, but it was very
deliberate for the purposes of streams.
And there was sort
of like a peak moment
where it got really into it.
But then I felt like a lot of impedance
mismatch where everything wanted to be
modeled as a stream, but
not everything is a stream.
Some things are just like a one-off
thing, and you just do an HTTP request
and you get it back.
Ensure that might fail, and eventually
you're just interested in one value, but
you kind of model your tree
tries, etc. as a stream, etc.
So this was my first exposure
really to this mindset, but it felt like
the gravity was too hard on
this very specific primitive.
And this is where I would rather like
create more distance between Effect and
RxJS, because Effect is not trying to
tell you, "Hey, everything is a stream."
No. Effect gives you a stream abstraction
that lets you use the stream abstraction
when you have a stream.
For example, when you use a WebSocket or
when you use something else, maybe you
want to read a file and use streams
through the bytes, etc.
This is where streams are a great use
case, but if you just want to do a
one-off thing that happens to be
asynchronous, then you don't need to be
forced that this is the
stream mindset, but this is where Effect
gives you different primitives.
And I think this is kind of the huge leap
beyond what RxJS gives you, and I think
this was always like the big caveat for
RxJS that not everyone buys into the
"everything is a stream" mindset.
And this is where Effect is much more
applicable to any sort of circumstance
where programming
languages is applicable to.
Very interesting to hear your perspective
on this. You've been
mentioning Cortex now a few times.
So before we dive into how it's built
specifically and how it leverages Effect,
can you motivate what Cortex is and what
role it plays within MasterClass?
Right, yes. So Masterclass has been
developing over the last year plus our
own in-house voice AI chat that has got
kind of a MasterClass twist to it,
and that you're not talking with
fictional, invented characters or
anonymous service bots, but we got
authorization from many of our
instructors who are working closely with
us to essentially clone
them into an AI persona.
This includes an LLM that is trained on
their ideas, their writings, their public
speaking, and it also
includes a voice clone of them.
And in some cases also, we have some
chefs like Gordon Ramsay is being
released soon, and we have a lot of his
recipes that are included, and he can
walk you through
making one of these recipes.
So it's a really interesting, interactive
way that I think enables MasterClass
instructors to make themselves really
available to a much broader audience than
they would be able to on
their own as individuals.
And so this has also presented an
enormous technical challenge because I
think when you are talking to an
anonymous AI, well, you might
be a little bit more forgiving.
You know that it's a bot that you're
speaking to on some level.
But with these real people who are very
invested in the integrity of their image
and their public persona, the bar is much
higher, I think, in terms
of really representing that.
And this is also like if you sign up and
you try to interact with Gordon Ramsay,
well, if you're a fan, how many times
have you seen him on TV?
You can watch the MasterClass courses,
you know, it's also
like more than an hour of content.
You know what he sounds like, you
know how he speaks, you know what he's
passionate about, what he doesn't like.
You know, this personality is something
that you've probably learned already. And
now we have to put that into an AI agent
or an AI bot that you can talk to.
And so I feel like the very similitude has
to really be there. And so that's been
really challenging just to kind of get
through the uncanny valley stage of that.
And so this is the background of what
we're building. If you want to try it
out, you can go to
oncall.masterclass.com, all one word
oncall, O-N-C-A-L-L, dot masterclass.com.
And you can sign up and try it out.
So this is the general product that we're
building. And we have a whole LLM team,
you know, a machine learning team that is
working on getting the voice models and
the LLM models really trained up to
represent each instructor.
And what I got brought on to do was
essentially to create an orchestration
layer because we have several different
components in the pipeline in order to
build this experience.
First, we have a speech-to-text component
where the end user's voice of microphone
stream is sent to a speech-to-text
service that then listens to the user's
speech and derives transcripts
from it of what they've said.
And then at certain intervals when we
believe that the user's done speaking and
is ready to hear what the AI has to say,
which is not a trivial problem, by the
way, we then send that transcript to the
LLM to generate a response.
And then the LLM generates text response,
and then we send that off to a text-to-speech
service to generate the audio for
that response in the instructor's voice
and then send that back to the user.
So we have several different
asynchronous services, the
speech-to-text and the text-to-speech
components of which are WebSockets.
And then the LLM is a HTTP streaming
connection essentially wrapped in an
async iterable in the JavaScript world.
So this is coordinating
between these different elements.
But as you can see, there's kind of a
step one, step two,
step three to this process.
What makes it kind of interesting is, as
I mentioned, we don't know if
the user is done talking yet.
The user can kind of start
talking again at any time.
What we want to do is shut down anything
the bot is doing at that point because
the user is supreme.
The user drives the conversation.
We don't want the bot talking over the
user when the user is
trying to say something.
And so it's really crucial that we are
very responsive to that and stop whatever
is in progress downstream, whether it's
at the LLM stage or
the text-to-speech stage.
And so this is
essentially what Cortex is doing.
Cortex is a Node.js application that is
connected to bi-WebSockets from our two
clients that we have, Web and iOS
clients, that connect
to Cortex over WebSocket.
And Cortex, in turn, provides WebSocket
interface that abstracts these multiple
services and receives the microphone
audio stream from the user
and emits back bot audio events.
So from the client's perspective, the
contract is simply send the user's
microphone audio to Cortex and receive
back the bot audio and then the clients
have to actually play
it through the speakers.
And that's kind of the, you know, the
whole the whole contract.
There's a couple of other details in
terms of, you know, if a tool call
happens or, you know, if state change
happens or something like that.
But that's the main gist of what that
WebSocket contract to
Cortex looks like under the hood.
However, Cortex has to orchestrate the
various services that I talked about,
execute tool calls and and do a whole
bunch of other, you know, state
management under the hood.
And so that's what we built with
Effect. It's 100 percent.
I mean, 100 percent. But like it's it's
pretty much the every piece of it is
built in Effect or
using Effect in some way.
That's awesome. So you've mentioned that
initially when you got into this project,
you got a first like proof of concept and
where it really like exposed you to all
of the complexity that's for solving this
actual product to
implement this actual product.
This complexity need to be tamed. Did you
work off that initial proof of concept or
did you rather roll
something from scratch?
And how did you go about that?
That's an interesting question because
I'm always trying to figure out how to.
Like re-architect a
piece of software, you know.
It's something you don't want
to have to do very often.
Also, I don't know, actually, if it's
me or just the stage of career I'm
at and the kind of problems that I get
brought in to help with.
But I often find myself looking at a
piece of software that is
in need of re-architecting.
I think it's largely because I was
specifically asked to
re-architect it in this situation.
But the proof of concept was interesting
because, you know, it was built by our
project lead on call, who
is now our VP of architecture, who's
just a brilliant person who has no
experience really with
JavaScript or TypeScript.
And asked chat GPT to help. I think it
was chat GPT to help with building it and
essentially just piece that all together
from chat GPT prompts.
There were a couple of things that came
out of that that were, for example, a
library that is like a private library
that isn't really maintained.
There wasn't really a
top level architecture.
you had individual pieces that
were kind of worked in isolation, but
then the glue between them became really
convoluted and hard to follow.
So so that that kind of became a problem.
But it worked. You know, ultimately, this
proof of concept kind
of worked for a demo.
It didn't handle interruptions very well.
It didn't have great latency.
I think in reality of like most
production grade systems are actually let
me take that back, probably not
production grade, but applications,
JavaScript applications that are running
in production are probably
That sort of state where is working well
enough on the happy path, but all of like
those higher level requirements that
really make a end user experience superb
that you can interrupt an AI model when
when it's talking to you or that's more
resilient to errors, etc.
This is where you need to go beyond that
convoluted everything
kind of pieced together.
And I think this is like a perfect point
to to start with, like
applying Effect to to go beyond that.
That's sort of like a messy state.
Yeah, this is why I wanted to
tame the asynchronous
behaviors in in Cortex.
And I was looking for a package that
would help me do that. And
this is when I found Effect.
And then at that point like I
said, I had seen RxJS. and I had
good experiences at
first building RxJS
But like kind of one of the common
complaints is that, well, now, like you
said, everything has to be a stream.
Now you have to model
everything in this way.
And it really completely changes how you
architect your software and you need a
lot of buy in from your team if you're
going to start doing this, because now
everybody has to learn this.
They can't just sit down and, you know,
start coding on whatever part, you know,
feature they're trying to do.
They have to first learn this framework
and that can be a big ask for folks.
And so that's something that I wanted to
be conscientious about.
However, when I started
looking into Effect, I started seeing,
well, you know, this has a lot of promise
and potential if you
use it in the right way.
And what I mean by that is like, you
know, you don't have to necessarily go
from zero percent to
100 percent overnight.
You don't have to completely redesign the
entire application to take advantage of
some of the benefits
that Effect has to offer.
That's kind of how I started, was
incrementally adopting
Effect in parts of the code base.
And this was really what
enabled it to work at all.
If I had to say, hold on, I need to take
this for a month and just completely
build it from scratch and nothing's going
to work and I can't deliver any new
features until I'm done.
That was not going to fly.
I was in a position
where I did not have to ask for
permission to go live in a cave for a
month or however long
it was going to take.
I always like avoid
being in that situation.
I don't think that's a good place for us
to be in as software engineers.
We need to be shipping like every day,
shipping features, shipping bug fixes,
shipping products constantly.
And like we never have the luxury to just
say, well, hold on, I'm just going to
like spend a month not shipping, you
know, to do this technical thing that I
can't really explain
why I have to do this.
Right. Nobody, nobody likes that.
So fortunately, Effect is not
a framework that is like that.
That's not what was
asked of us to adopt Effect.
Instead, it was you can start plugging in
Effect judiciously here and there.
And I started at the top level of the
application around really around the
WebSocket connection layer, around the
HTTP layer and the application runtime.
And that allowed us to kind of have a top
level of error handling that immediately
provided benefits for recovery and so on.
But we didn't stop there.
That was just the first step.
We started kind of rebuilding different
parts of the application.
Some of them were like isolated behind a
run promise or, you know, like a stream
that was, yeah, emitting
events into an event emitter.
But it allowed us to kind of rebuild
isolated parts of the application on
their own where like selectively where we
thought they had the most value to be
converted into Effect.
And often driven by product requirements.
So when I wanted to implement
interruptions, that was the reason to now
rebuild the speech-to-text component in
Effect, because it was going to be a lot
more work to do that.
If I was going to have to do it
the old way, it was like, really, it
wasn't like rebuild the whole thing
in Effect, the entire application.
Or just keep working the old way. It was
really for each isolated piece.
It was like, do I want to like add more
spaghetti to this application in this
component or can I just rebuild this
piece in Effect and make it much more
expressive and elegant while building the
feature that I'm being asked to build.
So it was much less of a refactoring
process and more of a incrementally
adopting it while also building and
delivering features.
I love that. And I think you've hit on a
couple of really nice points here.
One is that Effect, even though you get
a lot of benefits once you have
Effectified more and more of your
application, you're going to find that
you can delete a lot of code.
Everything just fits
nicely together in the same way.
If you incrementally adopt React, let's
say we're just in this transition of like
transitioning a larger code base from
jQuery, something else to React.
You don't need to do that in one like
long night, but you
can do that step by step.
And once you've reached a point where
everything is in React, then you can
delete a whole bunch of like glue code, a
whole bunch of like things that bridge
from the old way to the new way.
But it is also totally fine that you go
through this like transitionary phase.
But the other thing that you've mentioned
that I think is like a super great
insight, which is like, how do you
prioritize what to refactor with Effect
when or when to rethink
something and apply Effect?
And this is so elegant that you can like
go top down from like, hey, what is the
thing that we want to improve for users?
What is like the business outcome that we
want to affect here?
And then like looking at those, Effect
typically has
something in store for that.
If you want to improve performance, if
you want to improve reliability,
resilience, error handling, whatever it
might be, Effect typically
has something in store for that.
And then you can prioritize what to work
on depending on your end user needs.
And hearing here about the speech to text
aspect and applying Effect for that,
that sounds super interesting.
So I want to hear a little bit more like
zooming into from macro into a bit more
micro into this component.
Can you give a rough overview of like how
that thing was built before?
What you diagnosed the biggest things to
improve where and which primitives of
Effect did you use to
ultimately implement it?
Well, actually what I prefer to do is
zoom in on the text-to-speech component.
Oh, I'm sorry.
I remember that wrong.
But yes, no, it's okay.
You remembered it right.
It was you.
I said speech-to-text earlier, but I feel
like the text-to-speech component.
This is the component that I also talked
about in my Effect Days
talk and did a deep dive on.
I feel like the text-to-speech component
was kind of like a real unlock, really an
aha moment of like, wow, this is this is
what Effect can do in
terms of like saving
a lot of complexity from your code base.
As I mentioned, this is a
component where like it's a WebSocket and
we stream LLM thoughts to it.
So an LLM response, as you might be
familiar, it sends what are called chunks
in a chat completion response.
And the chunks are usually a token or two
tokens and they're not
complete words a lot of the time.
So then we're like accumulating the
chunks into basically what we call
coherent thoughts and the coherent
thoughts can then be sent to the text-to-
speech component to
generate the bot audio.
However, if there's an interruption, we
need to shut down the LLM and we also
need to shut down the
text-to-speech component so that we don't
continue to generate more thoughts based
on the previous thing that the user said
before they continued talking.
And now we want to start over and respond
to the most recent thing
that that user has said.
So the text-to-speech component now it's
a WebSocket connection.
When you send it a
coherent thought, that connection
will then respond asynchronously with one
or more different
events that you might get.
And we're basically just
streaming those up to the client.
But when there's
an interruption, we need to actually shut
down the WebSocket
connection, close the connection.
Abruptly, so we don't get any more
messages from it and then reopen it.
And then in that period of time, and it's
not usually very long, it can just be
like a hundred milliseconds or two
hundred milliseconds where we're waiting
for that WebSocket connection to open.
We hope that
we've created a connection, but we've not
yet received the open
event from the connection.
And it's in that time that we were often
getting the LLM was trying to send
messages to it, but it was erroring
because we were sending WebSocket
messages out to a
WebSocket that was not yet open.
So we had to now queue those messages to
wait for the open event from the
WebSocket connections and then flush the
queue when it was open.
So as you can imagine, this created some
code complexity in the pre-Effect
implementation and it was something that
Effect turned out to be actually very
good at because these are the kinds of
things that Effect has out of the box.
In Effect we were able to replace the
WebSocket handling code with the
WebSocket utility from
Effect from effect/platform APIs
And that has kind of a magical property
to it that you don't really ever have to
think about when the WebSocket is closing
and opening and you don't
have to wait for an open event.
What it essentially gives you is what is
called in Effect a channel.
And this became a primitive
that I became curious about.
It's something that I wish was a little
bit more first class in the effect world.
It's certainly used behind the scenes in
a lot of things like stream and other
APIs in the Effect world.
But this is what you get essentially when
you create a WebSocket connection using
the effect/platform API.
But then if you use the Effect stream
operator pipe through channel, you now
have a duplex stream, which is one where
you can start listening to other streams.
And then instead of doing like a run for
each or run collector, whatever you're
doing and you typically do it with a
stream, you now are piping the events or
the items in that stream out through the
channel through the WebSocket connection.
And then downstream from that pipe
through channel, you are getting incoming
events that are coming from that
WebSocket connection that you can then
emit further on down your application.
So this is great. But this is also what
it is also doing is this is abstracting
the WebSocket lifecycle
into the stream lifecycle.
So if you emit an error
upstream, it will close
the WebSocket for you.
And then if you have a stream.retry, it
will reopen the WebSocket for you
in the event of an error.
And because the streams are pull based,
you don't have to rely on queuing
explicitly. You aren't going
to miss any of your events.
When the stream is reopened, it will
start pulling those events
and behaving as expected.
So this really allowed us to
abstract all of the sort of tangled like
we had, I think, a promise that was a
reference to a promise that was kept
around and was
awaited in different places.
And it was it was a mess before. And now
we had a single stream that was just a
linear stream that where you had the
stuff going out, going in the top of the
stuff coming from the stream, coming out the bottom.
And it became very easy to reason about
what was happening. And you didn't really
even have to think about the stream
lifecycle at all. It was just you made an
error when you want it to
close and then just retry.
The WebSocket
connection is now handled by the stream
lifecycle. So you can use
the stream retry stream.
will be shut down when the
scope of the stream ends and the
WebSocket will automatically closed.
We also have a flush event that we send
out to the text-to-speech
service, which essentially says we're
done sending you a new speech for now.
So send us everything you got. And the
peculiarity of this particular service is
that they will then accept your flush
event and they will
promptly close the stream on you.
That's not really what we wanted, but I
don't know. They designed it this way.
And I don't really have, you know,
leverage to get them to redesign their
entire API. I just have to
work with what we have. Right.
This is a lot of application development.
You don't have the liberty to redesign
every API that you're working with. You
have to abstract it in some way. And so
this is what we're having to do here. But
the Effect stream
primitives make it really easy.
That sounds brilliant so far. And I think
what is so nice about this is
that it is A very clear and very
intuitive from a user perspective what
the system should do.
And as users, we're like all familiar
with when this goes wrong and how
frustrating it is. Like if I'm talking to
the AI, the AI goes off like in a wrong
direction that I don't want.
And I want to interrupt it.
And it doesn't act on this interruption.
You need to listen to it for another 20
seconds until I finally need to repeat
what I've just said.
And all of those things, they need to be
handled. And all of that is a lot of
complexity. And if you leave that
complexity unchecked, like you said, it
was a mess. And I think that nicely
reflects the majority of JavaScript
applications that are out there or
TypeScript applications.
And I think it's really like this
fine line to walk where you capture
all of like the existential complexity
that your use case requires and shaving
off like all the accidental complexity
and isolating this nicely.
And even to a degree where you say like,
okay, those services that you need to
call, they're not in the ideal shape that
you would like it to be. But then you can
just like wrap it and create your own
world that you're happy in and where you
can model your application in a nice way.
And yeah, I'm very happy to hear that
effect streams and the various primitives
that you've been using. You've been using
the WebSocket abstraction that Effect
gives you, and I
suppose also queues, etc.
That all of this has been so nicely
fitting together to model your use case.
So going a little bit beyond streams,
which other aspects of Effect have you
been using or which other kind of
superpowers have you been getting out of
Effect that have played a
meaningful role in the application?
Well, the error handling has been huge.
Honestly, we modeled all of our possible
errors. We have, I think, maybe up to 30
or so errors that the system can emit
that are domain specific tagged errors.
And those are decorated with a specific
error code and an error source, because
one of the things that will often happen
or that was happening originally, I
think, was, oh, we got an error. The
connection went down.
Well, we got an error and something weird
happened, and I don't know why, and now
I'm in a weird state. Oh, we got an
error, and the whole service just crashed
or something like this, right?
And even if you can just wrap everything
in a try catch, best case scenario, you
have some unrecoverable error, your
connection goes down, and you don't know
why. You just know, oops,
bye, and then all of a sudden.
And so it's frustrating for the user, and
it's also frustrating for the rest of the
team when they're trying to diagnose
what's going on, which we spent a lot of
time doing in our
development workflow internally.
And, you know, I'm a big fan of passing
the buck, so I don't like things to be my
fault. And I think
we're all in that domain.
I say this to joke, actually, I'm fine
with taking responsibility if it's my
fault, but I would rather things not go
wrong because of the
decisions that I made.
A lot of times early on, it was like,
oh, Cortex is down. Oh, Cortex emitted an
error that I don't understand.
And, you know, fair enough from a
client's perspective or from a test
engineer's perspective,
that's what it seems like.
But that doesn't really give you enough
information to troubleshoot because most
of the time it's not, you know, Cortex is
just a hub. Cortex is just passing events
from one service to another.
It's not Cortex really as the source of
the errors. Instead, what we see a lot of
the time is, oh, one of our
backend services went down.
Oh, a backend service emitted something
that we didn't expect. Oh, it's being
slow or something like this.
And now we're able to like create
targeted pinpoint errors whenever a
specific thing goes wrong
somewhere in the system.
And then those propagate up to our top
level error handling. And so if we have
something that's unrecoverable that
happens, we can now close
the connection like before.
But now we can send up detailed
information that allows our people to
diagnose what's the
problem. So it's not Cortex.
It's like, oh, our speech-to-text service
crashed or is out of memory or something.
And so now we aren't able to create calls
until we fix that
piece of infrastructure.
So that gives us a lot more information
that kind of actually saves a lot of time
debugging the system. It points you
directly to where the source of the
problem is instead of making
you go on a debugging hunt.
So that has been huge for us. The error
handling has been extremely valuable.
There are a lot of other errors that are
recoverable, but we want
it to log and report them.
So the whole error handling story in
Effect is fantastic, just surfacing when
things can go wrong and
forcing you to deal with it.
It has also meant, interestingly, I feel
like that, you know, like within Cortex,
not every function is an effect.
You know, not every single line of code
is a yield star. There's a fair amount of
just plain old, data manipulation
that is happening throughout the code.
It's data manipulation using
functions that are
synchronous and aren't going to throw.
Right. You could have very high
confidence that, you know, if you're
trying to get an index of a thing from a
string, you know, or
whatever, you're not going to throw.
you can do like a
lot of just kind of conventional
programming in areas that
are kind of safe and sandboxed.
And it doesn't mean that every single
calculation needs to be done in an
effect. It just gives you a safe place to
do that kind of work without having to
worry, you know, oh, if this throws or
oh, if this does something asynchronous
and I, you know, don't handle it, you
know, don't await it or whatever.
You know, usually those those kinds of
cases are they get a lot of attention
because we have to
think about them so much.
But that's not usually the most of the
work that we're doing. Ideally, right?
We're thinking about like, purely
functional transformations of data from
one state into another.
taking the input from
some kind of asynchronous effect and
sending it out to
some asynchronous effect.
But like the actual program, the business
logic is usually something that is like
pretty, you know, step by step, you know,
just just logic. Is usually when
we're not interfacing with an external,
you know, service or
some kind of side effect.
Then we can just write code like normal.
You know, we don't have to model
everything as a stream just to add up
some numbers or something.
Right. And I think that the super plain
way how you put it just write code like
normal. I think this is kind of the in a
nutshell, the difference
between Effect and RxJS
Where in RxJS you need to do everything
as a stream. And in Effect, you can write
code like normal. And another aspect of
writing code like normal
is trading errors as values.
This is we're all super used to just
passing around and
manipulating data. And somehow, we're
kind of brainwashed into
thinking that errors need to be like we
need something we need.
We're almost like paralyzed about like,
how should we deal with errors? But if
we're just trading errors as values as
well, errors as data and passing them
around and Effect just makes that easy by
giving us a separate channel
to deal with that error data.
And then, like you say, like you don't
want to you'd like to pass it along, then
it's just data that you pass along. So I
think that's just like code like it's
normal. I think that is like one of
Effect's superpowers.
And closely related to errors is like
having visibility into when errors happen
when something doesn't go as expected. So
and I think if I remember correctly, the
telemetry part the observability part has
also been a key aspect of
building Cortex and operating it.
So maybe can speak a little bit more to
how you do observability and telemetry
usually within MasterClass, particularly
within JavaScript applications and how
Effect has helped you to
maybe improve that even further.
Right. Yeah. So I sort of have to admit
that we don't have an excellent story for
the most part or before Cortex didn't
have an excellent story about
observability at MasterClass
in the JavaScript world.
We have a number of services.
We have we have a Raygun. We have New
Relic and we have Core Logics. We get our
logs to we send our logs to and we have.
So we have a bunch of observability
services for things like video. We have a
dedicated video monitoring service that
we integrate and
a few high value business.
Applications like that. We want to keep
an eye on, you know, error rates for
people visiting our home page or things
that are really
indicate business traffic, business
being impacted by
some technical problem.
However, usually that that amounts
to like something
that's easily reproducible.
And easily fixable usually and there's a
either some infrastructure that needs to
be restarted or code change that needs to
be rolled back or something like that.
Cortex really represents a new level of
complexity when it comes to understanding
what's going on internally. And I think
that a big reason for that is that it is
not a one shot HTTP server type of
application, but is instead
You know, a stream of streams and is
handling all of these asynchronous events
that are passing through it. It's not
directly doing much of any work. It's
just literally in between all these
services handing events
from one service to another.
So, as I mentioned before, when
things go wrong, they're mostly not going
wrong in Cortex. And likewise with
observability
where the system is spending time
doing work, it's mostly not spending time
inside of Cortex doing that work.
Cortex is instead, waiting for
events from other services. And so what
we're interested in measuring is not
really the conventional, I think,
telemetry story when it comes
to building tracing and spans.
I think this is a story that is also
baked into the default Effect telemetry
story, right? When you have a Effect dot
with span with a name, you know, and you
and you and you wrap
that around an Effect.
Well, that's great. That ensures that
that span or that Effect, the time that
it executes is going to be represented by
a span in your trace. And for most like
one shot type of actions that you might
perform, that works great,
which is most of the time.
If you're doing actual work within an
effect, within a one shot effect, then
that is the conventional way that you do
telemetry. We're not really doing that at
all in our telemetry
implementation in Cortex.
Instead, we're interested in measuring
time between events that are coming from
outside services. Cortex is the only
place where we can really gather this
information because it's the hub.
But Cortex isn't sitting around. We don't
have like an effect that is, you know,
sleeping until it gets a certain
notification from or an event from
another stream.
It wouldn't make any sense
to build the application that way.
And so it doesn't really make a lot of
sense to build our telemetry that way.
I suppose what we're doing with
Open telemetry is a little unconventional
in that a span doesn't represent Cortex
doing that work. Instead, it represents
usually really represents like the LLM is
working or the text-to-speech
service is working.
And we're just waiting for that. But it's
measured from Cortex, not from these
other services. But because
it's really all streams.
What we have to go on isn't an effect
that we're measuring. It is literally the
time between two events in those streams
that we're measuring. And so we really
had to roll a lot of our
own telemetry handling.
But, you know, we were going to have to
do this anyway,
ultimately, because when you have.
Let's say we're not using Effect. We're
using the original approach, the
non-Effect approach that is event
emitters everywhere, you know, WebSocket
event handlers and so forth.
You get a transcription from the speech
to text service and you want to start the
span of time that it takes that you're
measuring that it takes to.
Generate a response
to that transcription.
Well, you can have a central hub where
like maybe you're
collecting all of these events.
But you're starting that span in one
event handler and then you're entering
you're ending it in a different event
handler for a different service.
And so you need a place where you're
holding on to those references might be a
centralized location that is listening to
all of these events.
But then it becomes kind of tangled up
because you're having to.
Keep these references around and
keep them alive, from one
event handler to a
completely different event handler.
And this is an area where.
Yeah, we had to roll some of our own code
in Effect do it this way.
But I feel like Effect kind of made it
easier to do it this
way anyway.
Allowing us to have a kind of a
connection level, long lived reference to
these spans and then just manipulate
spans in what is essentially a stream dot
tap where we are listening to all of the
incoming events and then just
Starting and stopping them based on
which events are occurring.
It's not been perfect, honestly.
It has been a little error prone
sometimes and we've had to go in and kind
of tweak things when we
have unexpected behaviors.
It's an area that has provided immense
value for us, however.
It's given us a lot of insight into what
people are experiencing
if people are experiencing.
Really slow behaviors, slow responses.
If people are experiencing the bot is
talking over me or this sort of thing.
If we have errors somewhere in the
system, we can see exactly where and when
that happened and in what service and in
what part of that
services work it happened.
And we're able to trace, you know, what
was the sequence of of chunks
that were emitted by the LLM.
You know, how long did it take
for us to get that first
chunk out of it out of the LLM.
You know, comparing the user message in
the bot response and you know, if the
user interrupted the bot, how much of the
bot speech did the user here?
And so a lot of these questions that are
really of interest to the business and
also for us technically.
When it comes to how on call is being
used and how people are experiencing it
are really answered by the telemetry that
we've built using
Opentelemetry and Effect.
But,it's a very
custom system that I I don't know that it
has its optimal form yet.
And I also don't know that is necessarily
going to apply to
everybody in the same way.
I don't know. This is like I said, it's
it's it's a very custom system that is
built for our use case that will not
apply in most conventional applications.
But I think that's OK.
There's always special cases.
This makes sense. And, where
Opentelemetry or the previous
technologies that is based on Open
Sensors and Open Tracing, I believe those
were the two predecessor technologies
that merged into Opentelemetry.
Where they're historically coming from is
like from distributed tracing. And that
is typically in a
microservice kind of architecture.
We have one service request response
style calling into another
one, calling into another one.
So I think where those systems or this
technology shines historically, at least,
is on a request response pattern where
you just get that burned on charge that
that you know from like a
performance profiler in a single threaded
environment or a multi-threaded
environment, now we get it
over like a network boundary.
So this is where those shine. But going
beyond that for different modalities,
like for long running streams or I've
been also experimenting with using
OpenTelemetry in a front-end setting
where like a front-end session, you don't
have that request response, but you have
a front-end session.
For example, think about how you use
social media. You might be doomscrolling
for a very long time. So is your entire
session, is that the trace that you have
with possibly like thousands of spans?
Or where do you make cut basically? How
do you design your trace and your spans?
I think that is still something that
we're figuring out as an industry.
And it's been cool to hear about your
usage of it. And I think this also speaks
to the flexibility of Effect. Yes,
they're like default patterns make it
really easy and kind of trivial to
instrument your app out of the box.
But if you want to instrument it in a way
that's a little bit more specific to how
you would like to give your trace
meaning, that's possible as well.
Maybe taking a step back here for folks
who are curious about Opentelemetry and
like generally see the value in
observability, but maybe haven't taken
that leap yet themselves instrumenting
their app, which sort of guidance would
you offer to people what to focus on,
maybe what to initially leave out of the
picture just to get going?
Oh, that's a really good question. I feel
like the answers are going to be really
specific to your use case. And in the
case of an application like Cortex,
extremely custom. And we have spent a lot
of time refining and iterating on our
telemetry implementation. But most
applications probably
don't need that, honestly.
I think, especially in the
JavaScript world, there's both browser
and Node based auto instrumentations that
are available that do a lot out of the
box. So I feel like a lot of what I would
want to start with are the ends of the
application when your code is calling out
to another service or when you receive
events from the user.
Because that kind of determines the shape
of that user session or that interaction
that you might be
interested in measuring.
And then it will identify kind of
hotspots of like, oh, the user waited a
long time for this response or whatever,
what's up with that? And then you can
start to drill further.
And then the other thing that I think is
really super valuable is distributed
tracing where you are propagating a trace
across service boundaries. And sometimes
this is just, you know, you're
instrumenting in your browser application
or in your iOS application.
you're making calls out to your API service and
you want to see what's going on in the
API service as well during that time
period. You're propagating the trace from
your client to your server so that when
you see them all together,
you can kind of piece together.
Oh, the client called out to the server
and then the server made these database
calls and you can see that all in one
distributed trace. That's really super
valuable. So just focusing on the ends,
either incoming events or outgoing
service calls, and then making sure you
have your distributed trace propagation
set up correctly. Those would be the top
things I would recommend.
Right. I agree. And I think the benefits
of having a good observability story
for your application and for your system
is so manifold. Like it helps you with
correctness to kind of understand like,
oh, like something is not going well.
That you're not just like
completely in the dark and looking for
the needle in the haystack, but that you
actually have a great foundation to
figure out what went wrong.
That is the, I think the foundation where
people start leaning on observability
beyond just console log. But then also
like doesn't just help you with making
things correct or diagnosing when
something was not correct,
but also making it faster.
Like otherwise you might just know like,
okay, that API request has taken two
seconds, but why? And sometimes there's
like really counterintuitive situations.
It's very simple and very
easy to realize, oh,
this is why it's so slow.
And also speaking of AI, this will like
be a perfect foundation to give an AI
even more context what is going wrong and
let the AI iterate further and help you
make your app more
reliable and more performant.
One of the frontiers that we're going to
be exploring, I think now that we've
cracked the seal on observability is
integrating it with our existing data
analytics or our end user analytics that
we are already collecting.
In MasterClass we're a really good, robust data
team that is, you know, while respecting
like anonymity and user privacy is still
really invested in
understanding the user journey.
What are people doing? You know, why are
they there? What is enticing
them? What's driving them away? And these
sorts of questions that are really
foundational to understanding the best
way that we can
deliver value to our users.
Integrating this with a sort of Opentelemetry
will give us even more insights
of like, oh, did a user try to
load a page, but then they bounced
because it took too long to load and
things like this that will give us an
integration level between the sort of end user metrics
that we've been using and also the technical
implementations behind the scenes that
are underpinning that user experience.
I'm really looking forward to being able
to explore that further. And I feel like
it has tremendous
potential to offer value.
That sounds awesome. So speaking of a bit
more forward looking perspectives
I'm curious now that you've been part of
the Effect community, I think at this
point way beyond a year already and super
impressive what you've been able to build
with Effect in that short period of time.
What are the things that you're looking
forward most to when it
comes to the Effect ecosystem?
I'm really looking forward to seeing
Effect 4.0 come out. That looks awesome.
A lot of the improvements they've made to
the bundle size and to the implementation
complexity look really promising.
And, you know, I really admire how
responsive the Effect team has been to
the community, to the needs of the
community and really listening to
feedback, incorporating it, iterating.
That's really, I think, been vital to any
platform like this, getting any traction.
It's a very ambitious platform. It just
has to be said, the design of it to
encapsulate so much information about
what's going on at an atomic level in
your application, but then extending that
out into really
building whole frameworks.
The HTTP API, the Schema, the tracing
integration, the possibility that the
database abstractions, the networking
abstractions like WebSockets, file
system, node runtime,
there's React integrations.
Really, you name it, there's just tons
and tons of, and there's a whole bunch of
stuff coming in down the pipeline,
Cluster and AI integrations.
The paradigm is really extensible and it
has proven itself really robust and able
to handle all these different scenarios.
But now making all of those things all
work, you know, that's
an incredible challenge.
I hope something that they
succeed at. It's just so much.
But I think that with this large and
growing community, I think there will be
people using every aspect of that.
Probably not everybody is going to use
every piece of the Effect
ecosystem. I am not, certainly.
And most people will only use a small
sliver of it. And that's fine. That's all
you really need to do.
But when you have hundreds or thousands
of engineers all building different kinds
of applications with it, now you start to
get a lot more signal on
for this specific use case.
Here's what I'm trying to do.
Here's how I've approached it.
And that information, feeding that
information into the design of the
platform is going to be tremendously
valuable to making it more extensible.
But anyway, I'm really interested in the
Effect 4.0 developments that I think have
come out of this exact kind of feedback
integration and iteration.
And also, I'm really excited about things
like the, I think there was at the Effect
Days, there was some, there was a demo
that I think Mattia did.
Mattia, who did about the error reporting
and that was integrated into the editor
when there's like type errors in Effect.
Sometimes those can be cryptic and it's
nice to see that they're working on
making those a lot more
human readable and friendly.
It's nice to see the dev tools getting so
much love. It's nice to see the
documentation getting so much
improvement, so often very thankless.
Honestly, more than any specific
technical feature of the API, I just love
to see the developer
experience getting some attention.
And it makes things so much easier on
everybody to start building really cool,
ambitious things if you get really good,
clear, understandable errors at build
time or in your editor.
And if you have really good debugging
tools that let you understand what's
happening, if you have really good
documentation that has use cases and
examples of all kinds of different types
of patterns that you might
want to take advantage of.
This is the sort of, I think often unsexy
work of building a framework like this
that is so fundamental to people, like
end users being able
to get value out of it.
And it seems like the Effect team is
taking this seriously. And that to me,
more than almost anything, is what gives
me excitement and hope about
the future of this framework.
100%. I mean, I couldn't agree more.
They're all super ambitious efforts on
their own. And luckily, we have a small
but super talented and absolutely
brilliant core team of folks who are
working on the various pieces.
You've been mentioning the docs. We have
Giulio working more or less full time on
the docs as well as on the Effect Schema,
which we could probably also fill an
entire show on just talking about the
Effect Schema, which I
think you're also using.
Oh, yeah. We're using Effect Schema all
over the place. I didn't
even talk about that. Yeah.
Yeah. But then also the the dev tools.
I'm super excited that
Mattia will be joining.
Well, at the time of this recording, a
couple of days from now, but when the
time comes and the recording airs, I
think Mattia will have already started
working full time on the dev tools and
other pieces and improving
the developer experience.
And then at the core of all of it, Effect
4.0 and what it will enable. That's
really been the distillation
of all the feedback that we've gathered
over the last couple of years.
And I think really tackle some of the
most common points of feedback or
frustration head on. And I think it's
really like a huge improvement over
what's already really great and useful.
So I'm fully on board with with
everything you've you've shared. And
yeah, I think I can't thank you enough
for sharing all that what you've been
building with Cortex at MasterClass.
It's really, really impressive.
What you've been able to build in such a
short period of time speaks to
experience, but also speaks to just like
how capable the building blocks are. And
like when like experience and ambition
comes together with great materials.
I think this is how we're going to get
great experiences and great applications.
So thank you so much for doing that work
and sharing it.
And thank you so much for coming on the show today.
Well, thank you so much for having me.
And I just you know, I have to say that
so far, I think the on call product has
been a huge success and Cortex has been
very, very crucial part of that.
And I feel like it would not have been
possible without the Effect ecosystem and
also the support of the Effect core team
and the community to helping us get
there. I think that has played a fundamental
role. So thank you. I mean, to you,
Johannes, and thank you to the broader
Effect Team and the community for all of
the support and assistance and enthusiasm
and building this incredible framework.
It has really been a game changer.
That is awesome to
hear. Thank you so much.
Thank you.
Thank you for listening to the
Cause & Effect Podcast.
If you've enjoyed this episode, please
subscribe, leave a review
and share it with your friends.
If you haven't done so already, you can
join our Discord community.
And if you have any questions, feedback
or suggestions about this episode or
about Effect in general,
don't hesitate to get in touch.
See you in the next episode.